<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<rfc category="std" submissionType="IETF" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-rosenberg-dispatch-ripp-inbound-00">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="RIPP WebRTC">RIPP WebRTC Mode</title>

    <author fullname="Jonathan Rosenberg" initials="J.R." role="editor"
            surname="Rosenberg">
      <organization abbrev="Five9">Five9</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4000 Executive Parkway #400</street>
          <city>San Ramon</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94583</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jdrosen@jdrosen.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="January" year="2020" day="27"/>

    <area>Applications</area>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Real-Time Internet Peering Protocol (RIPP) defines a
      technique for establishing, terminating and otherwise managing
      calls between entities in differing administrative
      domains. The RIPP Inbound extension brings this to end clients,
      such as a browser. However, it defines a different technique for
      media that cannot directly use the webRTC APIs, and require a
      change to them. This specification provides an extension to RIPP
      for webRTC compatibility, enabling media to flow from browser to
      server as is done with RIPP, or from browser to browser. It also
      discusses techniques for sending e2e encrypted media.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

<middle>

<section title="Terminology">
<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
"OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here. </t>

</section>

<section title="Introduction">

</section>

<section title="Overview of Operation">

  <t>Basic idea: The TG indicates that this compatibility mode is
  supported on the TG. The handler is also indicates that this mode is
  supported. The handler includes its own ICE candidates. This means
  we provide the ICE candidates at "registration" time and not before
  the call. This is necessary to facilitate the many call move and
  other operations in RIPP-inbound. This also means the browser needs
  to keep them fresh all of the time, rather than just before the call
  [[is this posible with current API??]]. </t>

  <t>Since the media is sent by DTLS-SRTP and not embedded as media
  chunks in a client-to-server HTTPS connection, the browser includes
  its fingerprint in the handler as well. </t>

  <t>To initiate this compatibility mode for media, the server
  indicates as such in the directive. It can only put it in a
  directive if the handler that is selected, supports the mode. The
  directive includes the ICE candidates from the peer. This will
  trigger the client to perform ICE and send media (which will be
  DTLS-SRTP). </t>

  <t>RIPP itself doesnt convey the ICE candidates in the server to
  server link, since its only through handler whih is static for a
  device and not per-call. So we'd either need to move them, develop a
  separate way to convey them, or assume SIP or some other technique
  is used for server to server calls.
  </t>

  <t>Suggest we also require a well-known port for media, and we'll
  need an RTP headr extension to convey the callID since its included
  inband in RIPP.
  </t>

</section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>No values are assigned in this document, no registries are created,
      and there is no action assigned to the IANA by this document. </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document introduces no new security considerations. It is a
      process document about changes to the rules for certain corner
      cases in publishing IETF stream RFCs.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
<references title="Informative References">
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
</references>

  </back>
</rfc>

