<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<rfc category="std" submissionType="IETF" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-rosenberg-dispatch-ripp-phone-features-00">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="RIPP Phone Features">Enterprise Telephony Features in RIPP</title>

    <author fullname="Jonathan Rosenberg" initials="J.R." role="editor"
            surname="Rosenberg">
      <organization abbrev="Five9">Five9</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4000 Executive Parkway #400</street>
          <city>San Ramon</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94583</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jdrosen@jdrosen.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="January" year="2020" day="25"/>

    <area>Applications</area>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Real-Time Internet Peering Protocol (RIPP) defines a
      technique for establishing, terminating and otherwise managing
      calls between entities in differing administrative domains. This
      document extends RIPP by considering the specific case of an IP
      hardphone or softphone which connects to an IP PBX or similar
      piece of software. In this use case, additional signaling is
      needed for traditional telephony features, like hold, transfer,
      and park. This document extends RIPP to provide these
      capabilities.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

        <section title="Terminology">
   <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
   NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
   "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
   described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
   when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
   </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Introduction">
      
      <t> blah </t>

    </section>

<section title="Blind Transfer">

<t>Performs a blind transfer of the call. The event contains a string
which MUST be a valid value for the target URI parameter used when
setting up a new call. Once the transfer has initiated, the server
MUST generate a transfer-reject event if it is unwilling to perform
the transfer. If it attempts the transfer, it MUST send a
transfer-pending event indicating that the transfer is in
progress. If the transfer target answers the call, the server MUST
generate a transfer-success event, followed by an end event,
indicating the call is over for this user. If the transfer fails, the
server MUST generate a transfer-failed event, in which case the call
continues. Once the transfer target answers, it MUST be sent a
transferred-from event, containing the URI of the call from which the
transfer happened. </t>

</section>

<section title="Warm Transfer">

<t>transfer-warm: performs a warm transfer. For this to work, the
endpoint sending the event must be in two calls. It sends this event
on the one to be transferred to the other. The event has a single
parameter which specifies the URI of the call to which the transfer is
taking place. This two calls MUST have the same authority component of
their call URI. Once the peer receives this event, it MUST perform the
transfer. The transfer will either complete almost immediately else
fail. If it succeeds, the peer MUST respond with a transfer-success
event; if it fails, respond with a transfer-failed event, in which
case the call continues. Furthermore, if the transfer succeeds, the
transfer target MUST be sent a transferred-from event, containing the
URI of the call from which the transfer happened.</t>

</section>

<section title="Hold and Resume">

<t>hold: performs a call hold on the call. Either side can initiate this,
but only if its peer indicates support. Similarly, to inform its peer
that it has been placed on hold, either side may send an on-hold event
to its peer, but only if hold has been indicated as a capability. When
an endpoint has been told it is on-hold, it MUST send silence for
audio and black screen for video. The peer MAY generate music-on-hold
or any other suitable content to render while the endpoint is on hold.</t>

</section>

<section title="Mute">

<t>mute: informs the peer that it has muted. This is informative for UI
purposes, useful in conference calls for example. When an endpoint
mutes, in addition to sending the mute event, it MUST send silence for
audio and black screen for video. Similarly, if an endpoint wishes to
inform its peer that it is muting its media, it sends a mute event.</t>

</section>


    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>No values are assigned in this document, no registries are created,
      and there is no action assigned to the IANA by this document. </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document introduces no new security considerations. It is a
      process document about changes to the rules for certain corner
      cases in publishing IETF stream RFCs.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
<references title="Informative References">
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>
</references>

  </back>
</rfc>


