<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<rfc category="std" submissionType="IETF" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-rosenberg-dispatch-ripp-inbound-00">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="RIPP Inbound">RIPP for Single User Endpoints</title>

    <author fullname="Jonathan Rosenberg" initials="J.R." role="editor"
            surname="Rosenberg">
      <organization abbrev="Five9">Five9</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4000 Executive Parkway #400</street>
          <city>San Ramon</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94583</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jdrosen@jdrosen.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="January" year="2020" day="27"/>

    <area>Applications</area>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Real-Time Internet Peering Protocol (RIPP) defines a
      technique for establishing, terminating and otherwise managing
      calls between entities in differing administrative
      domains. While it can be used for single user devices like an IP
      phone, it requires the IP phone to have TLS certificates and be
      publically reachable with a DNS record. This specification
      remedies this by extending RIPP to enable clients to receive
      inbound calls through their outbound connection to the
      server. It also provides basic single-user features such as
      forking, call push and pull, third-party call controls, and call
      appearances. It describes techniques for resiliency of calls,
      especially for mobile clients with spotty network connectivity. </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

<middle>

<section title="Terminology">
<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
"OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here. </t>

</section>

<section title="Introduction">

  <t>The Real-Time Internet Peering Protocol (RIPP) defines a
  technique for establishing, terminating and otherwise managing calls
  between entities in differing administrative domains. It is an
  application ontop of HTTP/3, and as such has the notion of a client
  that opens connections and makes requests to a server. In the core
  RIPP specification, clients can only place outbound calls. Inbound
  calls are supported by requiring an entity to also run a
  server. </t>

  <t>While this requirement is appropriate for use cases like SIP
  trunking, carrier to carrier peering, or other arrangements
  involving a large number of calls, it is a poor match for single
  user devices. A single user device is one in which an actual end
  user would log in and use that device for making and receiving
  calls. Exampes include desktop softphones, browser based webRTC
  appications, IP hardphones, and video conferencing endpoints. These
  devices are often behind a NAT, dont have DNS names, and don't have
  TLS certificates, all of which are pre-requisiites to run a
  server. </t>

  <t>Furthermore, an end user may often be logged into multiple such
  devices, possibly from multiple locations. This introduces
  additional requirements. Inbound calls need to be forked to all
  devices, and ring on all of them. A user must be able to answer on
  one, and stop ringing on the others. SIP <xref target="RFC3261"/>
  natively supported these capabilities. However, it lacked other ones
  which are clearly needed - native support for mobile-based apps
  which utilize push notifications is one significant example. </t>

  <t>SIP's lack of call state in servers as a built-in feature of the
  protocol has also meant it couldn't readily support other features
  truly needed for a system where a user can be logged into multiple
  devices. These include the ability for one device to see the state
  of the call, and know on which other device the call is being
  handled. Another important feature includes the ability to - from
  any device - end the call, move it to a different device, or on the
  device the user is sitting on. It also includes basic third party
  call controls - the ability to initiate or answer a call from one
  client, but have the media delivered to another. </t>

  <t>To rememdy these challenges this specification provides an
  extension to RIPP to facilitate multi-user devices. </t>

</section>

<section title="Overview of Operation">

  <t>The actual protocol enhancement to RIPP is small. The primary one
  is enabling a server to inform the client of an inbound call, and to
  add additional events and supported event directions. The second one
  is additional behaviors required of clients around handlers.</t>

  <t>To signal usage of this specification, the server includes a new
  element, "inbound", in its TG description. The format of this
  element is identical to what it would look like to receive calls on
  a TG that would have been hosted by the single-user device, had it
  been able to do so. For example, the following TG describes a single
  user TG which can handle both outbound and inbound calls:</t>

  <figure>
    <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "outbound": {
    "origins" : "+14085551002",
    "destinations" : "*"
  },
  "inbound": {
    "destinations" : "+14085551002",
    "origins" : "*"
  }
}  
]]>
    </artwork>
  </figure>

  <t>The client will follow RIPP procedures for handler
  registration. This is analagous to the SIP REGISTER operation. For
  server to server peering arrangements, the handler represents a
  particular collection of capabilities on an SBC. When used by
  single-user devices, it represents each individual
  device. Consequently, if a user has four IP phones, there would be
  four handlers created on the server. As specified in RIPP each
  client needs to remember its handler URI persistently in order to
  modify it or delete it later on. </t>

  <t>Unlike SIP, wherein a client frequently refreshes its registrtion
  because it is soft-state, a RIPP client doesn't do this. Handlers
  are not soft-state, they are hard-state. A server can remove
  handler at will of course, but it is the responsibility of the
  client, through events or a query to its own handler URI, to learn
  of this and create a new one it if needed. Under normal
  conditions however, the server won't ever remove them. This is
  because receipt of inbound calls not tied to the existence of a
  handler, which is a substantially different model than used by
  SIP. Think of handlers like an inventory of a user's devices, solely
  for the purpose of an end user selecting amongst them when making or
  answering a call. As such, a server might delete one after extended
  inactivity (say, one month). But this is not necessary except to
  improve the user experience by eliminating old devices when a device
  list is too long. </t>

  <t>Unlike SIP-outbound, receipt on inbound calls doesnt rely on a
  client having a persistent connection to receive a call. RIPP does
  require a persistent connection for timely delivery of call events,
  but it does not have a functional dependency on it. For example,
  consider a client which lost its connection to the server for a few
  seconds, perhaps due to a fade-out in wireless connectivity. If an
  incoming call arrives at precisely that moment, the client wont
  receive its event. However, upon recovery of network connectivity,
  the client re-establishes its connection to the /events resource on
  the TG, performs the long-lived GET for events, receives an event
  about the calls in progress, including a new one that it is not
  aware of. This event includes the URI for the call. It queries the
  server, learns about the call, sees its state is "proceeding" and
  direction is "inbound". This tells the client to render the incoming
  call dialog. It can then answer and proceed with the call as
  normal. Indeed, the client can be out of network connectivity for as
  long as the caller is willing to wait for the call to be
  answered. This makes RIPP quite resilient to wireless network
  hiccups, network handoffs, and other network challenges which have
  become commonplace. </t>

  <t>In a similar way, the highly stateful nature of the RIPP server
  means that RIPP is also more resilient to mid-call drops in
  connectivity. A client which loses its network connectivity will, of
  course, fail to receive media, and its peer won't receive any
  either. To explicitly inform users of this, this specification
  introduces a new event, "reconnecting", which informs the client
  that its peer - which can be RIPP or SIP-based - has lost
  connectivity and reconnect is in progress. There is also a
  "reconnected" event that is sent to indicate reconnection. A server
  can determine when to send this based on any policy it so
  desires. It is used by the client solely for UI purposes. It
  encourages the end user to wait rather than hanging up. This allows
  the remote user to recover their network connectivity, or perhaps
  pull the call to another device. So, for example, a user might be on
  their call on mobile, lose connectivity when entering their
  home. They go to their wired PC, which will know about the call, and
  be able to hit a "pull call here" button or similar, and proceed
  with the call. </t>
  
  <t>The support of inbound calls on the TG means that the client can
  learn about incoming calls by performing a GET to the /events
  resource on the TG URI, as described in the core RIPP
  specification. This specification adds a new event, "call", which
  includes, as a parameter, the URI for the call that is now available
  to the client. The server will generate this event for both inbound
  and outbound calls, allowing any client that is retrieving these
  events to know about new calls.</t>

  <t>In order to receive inbound calls continuously, the client
  maintains its long-lived GET request to the /events resource. Of
  course, the client can learn about a new call through other means,
  such as through mobile push notifications. These need only deliver
  the call URI to the client, who can then query it and proceed from
  there.</t>

  <t>Once the client learns of this new call, it performs a GET on the
  call URI. This will provide the client with the call direction (in
  this case, inbound), calling party, destination number
  and most recent event (in this case, proceeding). This allows the
  client to render UI. </t>

  <t>With call state fetched, the client follows the procedures
  defined in RIPP, and establishes the signaling and media byways as
  normal. Once it starts alerting the user, it generates an "alerting"
  event towards the server. If it wishes to accept the call, it
  generates an "answered" event towards the server. The "answered"
  event, when sent by the client, includes a handler URI, which
  specifies the device on which the client would like the media to be
  rendered. Normally this will be itself. </t>

  <t>However, the client can specify a different handler. Any
  authorized client can learn about the handlers for the TG by
  querying the /handlers endpoint, which returns a list of them. The
  client can then iterate through them and request their details. It can
  also receive updates to the set of handlers using the /events
  resource on the TG. Specifying a different handler enables
  third-party call control operations. The image, device nickname and
  other attributes on the handler allow an end user to usefully select
  the device on which to receive the audio and/or video. </t>

  <t>In the case where, for example, a user answers a call and
  specifies a handler different from itself, the device associated
  with that handler needs to know about this. It will learn about this
  through its signaling byway to the call. It will see an "answered"
  event for a call, and then an "attaching" event with the handler
  URI. When the client sees that the handler URI is itself, this tells
  it that it must render media. To do so, it queries the call URI,
  which will return to it the directive to use. It also begins to
  accept media from the server. 
  </t>

</section>

<section title="Example Use Cases">

  <t>This section outlines example use cases that are enabled by this
  specification. It is not normative in nature. It merely describes
  how the new API features defined by this specification can be used
  by clients to deal with these cases.</t>

  <section title="Inbound Call Forking">

  </section>

  <section title="Answer and Stop Ringing Other Devices">

  </section>

  <section title="Remote in Use">

  </section>

  <section title="Call Pull">

  </section>

  <section title="Call Push">

  </section>

  <section title="Select Device">

  </section>

  <section title="3PCC: Place Outbound">

  </section>

  <section title="3PCC: Answer or Decline Inbound">

  </section>

  <section title="3PCC: Hangup">

  </section>

  <section title="3PCC: Move Call">

  </section>

  <section title="Resiliency: Miss Incoming call">

  </section>

  <section title="Resiliency: Mid-Call Network Change">

  </section>

  <section title="Resiliency: Mid-Call Wireless Fade and Recover">

  </section>

  <section title="Resiliency: Mid-Call Wireless Fade and Move">

  </section>

  <section title="Resiliency: Mid-Call Wireless Fade and Peer Hangup">

  </section>

  <section title="Resiliency: Mid-Call Wireless Fade and Server Drop">

  </section>

</section>

<section title="Normative Protocol Specification">

  <t>A server that supports inbound calls on its TG MUST include the
  "inbound" element in its TG description. This MUST include the
  allowed caller IDs in the "origins" element, and the allowed
  destinations in the "destinations". </t>

  <t>When a server receives a new inbound call, or places a new
  outbound call, it MUST send the "call" event to any clients which
  have a GET query in progress to its TG. This event MUST include the
  call URI associated with the call that the server is aware of. The
  server can also utilize push notifications or other techniques
  outside the scope of this speification to alert clients to new
  calls. </t>

  <t>The server MUST allow the client to send a "proceeding",
  "alerting", "answered", "declined", "failed", "noanswer" and "end"
  events, and take the associated actions on the call.</t>

  <t>A client that answers a call MUST include, as an attribute to the
  "answered" event, the handler that is to be used for the call. This
  handler MUST be active and registered to the TG against which the
  call was received. The server MUST verify this, and if it is not,
  generate a "handler-invalid" event, with the handler URI from the
  request as a parameter. In this case, the server MUST NOT consider
  the call answered. If the handler URI was valid, the server MUST
  construct a directive per the procedures defined in the core RIPP
  specification. It MUST then generate an "attaching" event to all
  listeners, and MUST include the handler URI. It MUST also generate
  the "answered" event. 
  </t>

  <t>When a client that had sent an "answered" event receives a
  "handler-invalid" event including the URI it had generated, it
  SHOULD refresh its list of handlers, inform the user of the answer
  failure, and request the user to try again. If the client receives an
  "attaching" event, and the handler specified matches its own, it
  SHOULD query the call URI to obtain the directive [[OPEN ISSUE: Not
  sure I like this, vs. having the client do a POST and have the
  server construct the directive then. Thinking.]] It
  MUST initiate signaling and media byways for the call, render
  incoming media and generate outgoing media for the call. Once the
  client has sent and received at least one media packet, indicating a
  successful connection, it MUST generate a "handler-connected" event,
  including the URI of its handler. As will all call events, this is
  sent to all listeners. This allows for a reliable handshake for
  answering calls elsewhere.
  </t>

  <t>Similarly, a client MAY, when creating a call, specify a handler
  in the POST to create the call which is different than itself. When
  it does that, it follows the procedures defined in the previous
  paragraph as well.</t>

  <t>A server MAY send, at its own discretion, a "reconnecting" event
  if it believes the remote side has lost connectivity. It is
  RECOMMENDED that the server send this event once it has ceased to
  receive inbound media packets for five seconds. Similarly, a server
  MUST send a subsequent "reconnected" event once media begins to flow
  once more. If a server receives a new GET request against the
  /events resource on the call, it MUST include the "reconnecting"
  event if it had sent one recently but not yet sent the "reconnected
  event. This allows a client to obtain the full state of the call
  when retrieving events.
  </t>
  

</section>

<section title="Syntax">

  <t>This specification outlines the syntax for the new events and TG
  description. </t>

</section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>No values are assigned in this document, no registries are created,
      and there is no action assigned to the IANA by this document. </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document introduces no new security considerations. It is a
      process document about changes to the rules for certain corner
      cases in publishing IETF stream RFCs.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
<references title="Informative References">
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
</references>

  </back>
</rfc>

